<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Anmol Gupta</title><link>https://anmolgupta.github.io/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Anmol Gupta</description><generator>Hugo 0.154.5</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:34:17 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://anmolgupta.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>CAG vs RAG: A Developer's Journey</title><link>https://anmolgupta.github.io/blog/cagvsrag/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:34:17 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://anmolgupta.github.io/blog/cagvsrag/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="starting-with-cursor"&gt;Starting with Cursor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many developers in early 2025, I jumped into Cursor. The auto-suggest feature was impressive in theory, but here&amp;rsquo;s the thing—it kept nudging me toward its suggestions on every single line. I found myself constantly fighting against the flow rather than going with it. So I turned off auto-suggest entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was that the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; choice? Who knows. But it worked for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With auto-suggest off, I started using Cursor more selectively—writing the structure myself and calling on it when I needed help with specific functions or integrating services. It made me more productive, though I couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite measure by how much. (Sound familiar? We&amp;rsquo;re all trying to figure out how to quantify AI-assisted productivity.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I discovered Cursor&amp;rsquo;s planning feature. This was interesting—I could plan out features before diving into code. But I noticed something: it kept suggesting patterns from my existing codebase. Great for consistency, not so great for exploring new approaches. I rarely got to see what else was out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: My experience spans Feb 2025 to Dec 2025. Cursor has probably evolved since then. If you&amp;rsquo;ve had different experiences, I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="discovering-claude-code"&gt;Discovering Claude Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around September 2025, I started experimenting with Claude Code. I was already using Cursor outside its main auto-suggest capability, so why not try something different?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, the planning experience felt similar—suggestions based on existing code patterns. But then I found something that clicked for me: when I explicitly asked Claude Code to show me patterns &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; my current codebase during planning, it actually did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, I had options. I could look at a feature implementation from two or three different angles, choose the one that fit both my taste and my team&amp;rsquo;s preferences, and this is the part I really valued—justify my choices with confidence. Every approach has trade-offs, but now I understood what I was trading and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got invested. I built custom commands, skills, and workflows. One of my favorites is a &lt;code&gt;/research&lt;/code&gt; command that tells Claude to search the internet for answers rather than defaulting to the current codebase or context. It changed how I approached problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hitting-the-context-ceiling"&gt;Hitting the Context Ceiling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where it gets interesting. As my project grew, the benefits I was getting from Claude Code started diminishing. The codebase was simply getting too large for the context window to handle effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started thinking about RAG (Retrieval-Augmented Generation). But wait—wasn&amp;rsquo;t that exactly what Cursor was doing all along? Searching my codebase and retrieving relevant context?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to Cursor. And you know what? It worked better this time. The project had matured. Patterns were established. Having RAG-style retrieval over a well-structured codebase actually made sense now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="cag-vs-rag-its-not-about-picking-a-winner"&gt;CAG vs RAG: It&amp;rsquo;s Not About Picking a Winner&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back at this journey, another developer might look at my choices and disagree completely. And that&amp;rsquo;s okay. The trade-offs I made were based on my situation at that moment: the scale of the project, team size and expertise, time constraints, and cost considerations. None of those things stay constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So which is better: RAG or CAG (Context-Augmented Generation)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think that&amp;rsquo;s the right question. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CAG feels more powerful when you&amp;rsquo;re in exploration mode—researching, innovating, trying new approaches. Yes, you&amp;rsquo;re limited by context window size. But isn&amp;rsquo;t that constraint similar to what the industry already deals with? Large monolithic codebases become unmanageable, so we split them into microservices. Smaller contexts, distributed ownership, freedom to experiment within boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG shines when you have an established codebase with clear patterns. It&amp;rsquo;s great for consistency and for working within existing structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="where-do-you-want-to-invest"&gt;Where Do You Want to Invest?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the real question is: where do you want to put your effort?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you okay with the network overhead of a microservice architecture while making a smaller investment in AI tooling with CAG? Or would you rather invest more heavily in RAG infrastructure to support a larger, unified codebase with minimal network complexity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no universal answer. Your mileage will vary. Your project will change. Your needs will evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the one thing I&amp;rsquo;m confident about: the situation will never stay the same, and the best approach is to stay adaptable rather than loyal to any single tool or strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your experience been? I&amp;rsquo;d genuinely like to know.&lt;/p&gt;
 </description></item></channel></rss>